<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>machine-learning on Joseph Daws</title>
    <link>https://joedaws.github.io/tags/machine-learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in machine-learning on Joseph Daws</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 May 2019 11:36:57 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://joedaws.github.io/tags/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Polynomial Inspired Neural Network Design and Initiailzation</title>
      <link>https://joedaws.github.io/post/binary-tree-network/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2019 11:36:57 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://joedaws.github.io/post/binary-tree-network/</guid>
      <description>Polynomial approximation can inform network design The following is a breif discussion of work found in this preprint which has been submitted to NeurIPS 2019. In this post I&amp;rsquo;ve left out many details. If you are interested in these details please see the preprint. As described in my previous post Neural networks have emerged as a very powerful tool for constructing nonlinear functions in high-dimensions. They are known to be very expressive in the sense that the class of functions they can approximate is very wide.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Designing Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://joedaws.github.io/post/designing-neural-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2018 15:23:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://joedaws.github.io/post/designing-neural-networks/</guid>
      <description>Towards a mathematical understanding of using neural networks for function approximation.  An artificial neural network (ANN) is a computational framework inspired by the interactions of neurons in the brain.
 Recently many difficult problems have been effectively solved using algorithms and mathematical models which iteratively improve their performance based on data rather than explicitly finding a solution. Such methods, which primarily rely on data rather than explicit solution techniques, can be grouped together under the umbrella of Machine Learning.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>